{"tossups": [{"question": "During this man\u2019s successor\u2019s time in power, the 13 Martyrs of Arad were killed, during which the executioners supposedly clinked their beer mugs while doing it, and to this day, the people in this man\u2019s country do not clink glasses while drinking beer. This leader paradoxically issued the first law protecting minority rights in Europe, but insisted that his culture was superior to Slavic cultures. \u00a0Before taking power, the government of his country began issuing the newspaper Vil\u00e1g to attempt to counter the liberal Pesti H\u00edrlap this man edited. This man wrote the Cassandra letter to criticize (*) Ferenc (\u201cfair-ence\u201d) De\u00e1k. This leader abolished serfdom in the April Laws. After abdicating his highest post, this man toured the US and Britain advocating for Magyar independence. For 10 points, name this Governor-President of Hungary during the 1848 revolution.", "answer": "Lajos Kossuth", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Lajos Kossuth</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Lajos Kossuth"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In Chapter 26 of Following the Equator, Mark Twain marvels at how an English traveler did not have an encounter with this group. This group did most of their work at locations called beles. The capture and compliance of one-time member of this group Feringhea by William Sleeman was one of the turning points in bringing about their downfall. This group was known for their use of a rum\u0101l with a coin in it, a skill which gave them the alternate name phansigars, or (*) \u201cnoose-operators\u201d. The legacy of this group was the main impetus behind the several Criminal Tribes Acts, though they had already been suppressed under an eponymous act that also targeted the similar dacoits. For 10 points, identify this Indian criminal organization whose Hindu members were primarily devoted to Kali.", "answer": "Thugees (a pronunciation like \u201ctug\u201d is closer to the original, but accept the anglicized \u201cth\u201d as in \u201cthin\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Thugees</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Thugees"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "a pronunciation like \u201ctug\u201d is closer to the original, but accept the anglicized \u201cth\u201d as in \u201cthin\u201d"}, {"question": "An action that indirectly aided this cause was when 203 families were chosen from the Midwest to settle in the Matanuska Valley due to their familiarity with cold. Entrepreneur Austin Lathrop opposed this action because he believed it would harm business by increasing the tax base. James Wickersham used the Ballinger-Pinchot affair to drum up support for this process, leading to a second Organic Act for the (*) territory in question. A very similar action occurred to the south in the same year, 1959, to balance Republicans and Democrats in Congress. For 10 points, name this process that added the 49th star to the American flag.", "answer": "Alaskan statehood (accept equivalents)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Alaskan statehood</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Alaskan statehood"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents"}, {"question": "Two answers required One of these people brought a young Simonides of Keos to his city, who later sought refuge in Thessaly after the assassination of a member of these people. That same person of this group got revenge on his love interest by making that man\u2019s sister kanephoros for a festival, then publicly revealing her ineligibility because she wasn\u2019t a virgin, an offense that led to his murder. Another of these people formed an alliance with the tyrant of Lampsakos, and would later use this alliance after being deposed by a Spartan army. After fleeing to the court of (*) Artaphernes, the older member of this duo suggested landing the Persian army at Bay of Marathon, leading to the namesake 490 BCE battle, and outlived his younger brother who was killed by the Tyrannicides. For 10 points, name these two men who jointly ruled Athens from 527-510 BCE, the sons of Peisistratos.", "answer": "Hippias and Hipparchus (accept answers saying that they are Peisistratos\u2019 children before Peisistratos is mentioned)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hippias and Hipparchus</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hippias and Hipparchus"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept answers saying that they are Peisistratos\u2019 children before Peisistratos is mentioned"}, {"question": "A painting of a notable event for this cause was controversial for its striking resemblance to the painting 1807, Friedland by Ernest Meissonier. It\u2019s not related to Chile or Peru, but the British admiral Thomas Cochrane commanded a navy fighting for this cause and led it to victory at the Battle of 4 May. A major event for this cause involved the removal of symbolic blue and white armbands and happened when and where it did because of a letter sent by Maria Leopoldina. This cause was opposed by Jorge Avilez\u2019s namesake rebellion, which was defeated after his forces were surrounded on Mt. Castelo. The (*) Duke of Caxias began his military career fighting for this cause and participated in the capture of Salvador, the capital of Bahia. Famously declared by Dom Pedro I during the Cry of Ipiranga, for 10 points, identify this cause that created South America\u2019s largest country.", "answer": "Brazilian independence (accept equivalents)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Brazilian independence</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Brazilian independence"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents"}, {"question": "Henry Rawlinson tried to prove that this city was preceded by one of the same name in a different location, but it is now known that he was dealing with the city of Gazaca. A king who ruled from this city apocryphally had a prophetic dream in which his daughter\u2019s urine flooded his kingdom, foreshadowing his grandson\u2019s conquest of his domain, and when a general of his refused to kill that grandson, he forced the general to eat his own son. This city was supposedly built with seven walls, each a different color. After his son Philotas was caught conspiring against Alexander the Great, the Macedonian general Parmenion was killed in this city. This city was taken by (*) Cyrus the Great after defeating its ruler, his grandfather Astyages. For 10 points, name this Iranian city that served as a capital for the Parthians, Achaemenids, and Medes.", "answer": "Ecbatana (accept Hangmatana)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ecbatana</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ecbatana"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Hangmatana"}, {"question": "In Harry Turtledove\u2019s Southern Victory Series, this man is elected president in 1936 as a Socialist candidate. Later in life, this politician served as president of the company that built the Empire State Building. This man owed much of his early political experience to Tammany Hall boss \u201cSilent\u201d Charles Murphy. In this man\u2019s highest post, William Randolph Hearst attacked him for not reducing the price of milk. Under Robert Wagner, this politician served as co-chair of the commission that investigated the (*) Triangle Shirtwaist fire. This \u201cwet\u201d politician lost an election because of \u201cthe three P\u2019s: Prohibition, Prejudice, and Prosperity\u201d. For 10 points, name this Democrat, Catholic, and loser of the 1928 presidential election to Herbert Hoover.", "answer": "Alfred Emmanuel \u201cAl\u201d Smith", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Alfred Emmanuel \u201cAl\u201d Smith</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Alfred Emmanuel \u201cAl\u201d Smith"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A leader of this event wrote the Letter from beneath the Gallows after being betrayed by one of his soldiers. The failure of this event prompted the development of \u201corganic work\u201d, a philosophy stressing cultural and economic improvement over armed rebellion. Two years prior to this event, the namestnik Karl Lambert declared martial law after a series of riots in places like Horod\u0142o. One of the proximal causes of this event was a conscription order issued by Aleksander Wielopolski. The author Apollo (*) Korzeniowski was one of many sybiraks exiled to northern Russia and Siberia for his participation in this event. This event saw the defenestration of Chopin\u2019s piano. For 10 points, identify this 1863 Polish rebellion against Russia named for the first month of the year.", "answer": "January Uprising (accept equivalents for uprising)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>January Uprising</u></b>", "acceptable": ["January Uprising"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents for uprising"}, {"question": "The earliest known domestication of cats occurred in this place around 7500 BCE. A stela at Kition tells of Sargon II\u2019s victory over seven kings of this place. This place was unusually ruled by an Arab-Byzantine condominium from the 7th to 10th centuries, which ended after the successful campaign of Niketas Chalkoutzes. The city of Enkomi in this place may have been the capital of Alashiya. The Ottoman period of rule of this island began after the Siege of (*) Famagusta. Richard I captured this island from the rebellious Isaac Comnenus and soon sold it to the Templars. In the 20th century, this island\u2019s close cultural connections with Greece have fostered a movement of unification, or enosis, with it. For 10 points, name this eastern Mediterranean island now split between the Turkish northeast and the Greek southwest.", "answer": "Cyprus", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Cyprus</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Cyprus"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One ruler of this polity legitimized his power by acquiring the twelve most powerful sampy religious idols in the kingdom. A king of this polity defeated the Vazimba people to take one of the twelve sacred hills of this polity\u2019s namesake ethnic group. Fran\u00e7ois Callet wrote down the oral histories of the noble class of this kingdom in the Tantara ny Andriana. A ruler of this kingdom defeated a joint British-French invasion and lined the beach around the port of Tamataye with the heads of 21 defeated Europeans. That ruler was called a (*) \u201cfemale Caligula\u201d. King Andrianjaka established Antananarivo as the capital of this kingdom. Ruled by three queens named Ranavalona in the 19th century, for 10 points, name this last and most powerful native kingdom of Madagascar prior to French colonization.", "answer": "Kingdom of Merina (accept Imerina)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kingdom of Merina</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kingdom of Merina"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Imerina"}, {"question": "An alternate name for one ruler of this state is now used as an insult to describe someone as a failure and that ruler was granted the title \u201cDuke of Anle\u201d after being deposed. A royal advisor of this state supported the rebellion of Zhong Hui in a rival kingdom after the fall of this state. During a campaign fought to avenge the loss of Jing Province and the death of a prominent general at Maicheng, this state lost the Battle of Xiaoting due to a fire attack engineered by Lu Xun (\u201cshoon\u201d). A general of this kingdom was victorious in one battle after he faked his death to lure an enemy army into attacking at the (*) Wuzhang Plains, completing the last of five expeditions against the kingdom of Wei led by Zhuge Liang. With Zhang Fei and Guan Yu in a novel by Luo Guanzhong, the founder of this state swore the Oath of the Peach Garden. For 10 points, identify this 3rd century CE state centered in modern Sichuan, the member of the Three Kingdoms founded by Liu Bei.", "answer": "Shu Han (prompt on Han or descriptive answers)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Shu Han</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Shu Han"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Han or descriptive answers"}, {"question": "An important story in this religion may have arisen from the tale of the death of Gavaevodata in a different tradition. Places of worship in this religion have often been found with depictions of lion-headed men with one or more snakes wrapping around them. Members of this non-Christian religion were called syndexioi, or \u201cthose united by a handshake\u201d and (*) Plutarch claims that this religion has its origin among the Cilician pirates. Cautes and Cautopates provide the light needed for an important action in this religion carried out by its main god in a cave. The primary deity of this religion was often depicted in a Phrygian cap slaying a bull. For 10 points, name this religion originating in Persia that was popular among Roman soldiers.", "answer": "Mithraism (accept Mithra worship, Mithraic mysteries, or other equivalent answers)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mithraism</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Mithraism"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Mithra worship, Mithraic mysteries, or other equivalent answers"}, {"question": "This dynasty lost its core territory with the accession of a woman whose name meant \u201cTree of Pearls\u201d who was later beaten to death with wooden shoes. This dynasty presented an invading force with generous peace terms after losing a key port, but they were rejected due to the objections of Pelagio Galvani. Maimonides served as the court physician for the early rulers of this dynasty. The early years of this dynasty were marked by a power struggle between the brothers al-Afdal, al-Aziz Uthman, and az-Zahir. This dynasty lost much territory to the (*) Abbasid-supported Rasulid dynasty. The founder of this dynasty was a vassal of Nur ad-Din and defeated Guy of Lusignan and Raynald of Ch\u00e2tillon at the Battle of Hattin. For 10 points, identify this dynasty in power from 1171-1250 that was founded by Saladin.", "answer": "Ayyubid Dynasty", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ayyubid Dynasty</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ayyubid Dynasty"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man was allowed to conduct an expedition in Russia on the condition that he did not publish anything on the condition of the serfs, and that expedition was briefly stopped by an anthrax outbreak. This man\u2019s work led to a world isotherm map created by William Channing Woodbridge. He observed a transit of Mercury at Callao and his writings were a primary reason for the use of guano as a fertilizer. This man\u2019s lectures at the University of (*) Berlin were published in a work called Kosmos. He climbed El \u00c1vila Mountain with the poet Andr\u00e9s Bello, the tutor of Sim\u00f3n Bol\u00edvar. Among other things, this man names a type of squid, a penguin, and a river in Nevada. For 10 points, name this Prussian explorer and naturalist who names various animals as well as a current off the west coast of South America.", "answer": "Alexander von Humboldt", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Alexander von Humboldt</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Alexander von Humboldt"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Former army doctor Giuseppe Ferlini destroyed over forty of this region\u2019s most famous structures in the 1840\u2019s to loot them of their gold. A city in this region has been called the \u201cBirmingham\u201d of its continent for its extensive ironworks and acquired a bust of Augustus during a raid on Syene. The Medjay people came from this region and served as scouts and a police force in a neighboring kingdom. King Kashta ruled a native state in this region from a city that had been founded by a foreign power; that city was (*) Napata. A kingdom in this region coordinated an attack on its northern neighbor with the Hyksos, and after its conquest by Thutmosis I, was ruled by Egypt until the rise of Kush. For 10 points, what was this region of Africa between the First and Sixth Cataracts of the Nile in modern Sudan?", "answer": "Nubia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Nubia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Nubia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The New York World ran an article about how a Private Lapeer was infected by the enemy with leprosy during this conflict, which is now believed to be fabricated because of the similarity of \u201cLapeer\u201d and \u201cleper\u201d. Papa Isio was a babaylan who led a force of pulahanes, believers in a syncretic Catholic/indigenous religion, in this conflict. This war was the continuation of a conflict begun by the Cry of Pugadlawin and the organization Katipunan. Gen. Jacob Smith was court-martialed for retaliating against a massacre on Samar by his (*) \u201ckill everyone over ten\u201d policy. This war ended shortly after the surrender of Gen. Miguel Malvar, which occurred a year after Emilio Aguinaldo was captured. For 10 points, identify this 1899-1902 war between a Pacific archipelago and its colonial master that had just won it from Spain.", "answer": "Philippine-American War or Philippine War of Independence", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Philippine-American War or Philippine War of Independence</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Philippine-American War or Philippine War of Independence"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "During the Long Winter, this place served as the base and last refuge of a king who secretly entered enemy camps to kill foes with his bare hands. A hill of dead soldiers called the Death Down was formed after a battle at this place by a force of Huorns. A force of infantry relieved a siege of this place under Erkenbrand, who had earlier lost a key ford over the Isen. The horn of a ruler with the epithet (*) \u201cHammerhand\u201d was kept in this place. This fortress was breached by an explosion in its drainage culvert and was nearly lost to an army of Dunlendings, Orcs, and Uruk-hai before Gandalf arrived with an army at dawn. For 10 points, identify this place, the primary fortress of Rohan and the scene of the climactic battle in The Two Towers.", "answer": "Hornburg (accept Helm\u2019s Deep since the movies use the name of the valley it\u2019s in as the name of the fortress)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hornburg</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hornburg"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Helm\u2019s Deep since the movies use the name of the valley it\u2019s in as the name of the fortress"}, {"question": "A widowed noblewoman from this region got revenge on the king who killed her husband by leading a fleet of black ships in a raiding and decapitating spree along the north coast of his country, becoming known as either the \u201cLioness\u201d or \u201cTigress\u201d of this region. A priest from this region compiled the world\u2019s first trilingual dictionary. Spendthrift and child serial killer Gilles de Rais moved to this region after a royal decree banned anyone from entering into contracts with him. This non-Flanders region fought in the rebellion of 1173-74 against Henry II of England. The term (*) \u201cBonnets Rouges\u201d names two separate anti-tax movements in this region, the first of which saw the destruction of an entire street accused of sedition in this region\u2019s capital of Rennes. Francis I incorporated this region on the Armorican Peninsula into his kingdom in 1532. For 10 points, name this region of northwestern France.", "answer": "Brittany (or Bretagne)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Brittany</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Brittany"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Bretagne"}, {"question": "One engagement fought by this ethnic group, the Battle of Hingakaka, was precipitated by a dispute over kahawai and saw the sacred Te Uenuku become lost for about 100 years. Whina Cooper led a protest march for this people\u2019s right to land in 1975. This ethnic group constructed an earthwork fort, or p\u0101, on One Tree Hill that now overlooks a city they call (*) T\u0101maki Makaurau. Contact between this people and the Pakeha declined after the Boyd Massacre, and these people were the progenitors, and later enslavers, of the Moriori people of the Chatham Islands. For 10 points, this is what people who exterminated the moa as the first inhabitants of New Zealand?", "answer": "M\u0101ori", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>M\u0101ori</u></b>", "acceptable": ["M\u0101ori"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The Cascajal Block may show the first evidence of this activity in the Americas. Julia Guernsey claims that artifacts from the Izapan culture show little evidence for this activity because it lay at the junction of two cultural regions. This non-sacrificial activity is first attested in Zapotec culture on Monument 3 at San Jos\u00e9 Mogote on a \u201cDanzante\u201d stela. Mayans who engaged in this activity were called aj tz\u2019ib (\u201cakh tseeb\u201d) and usually did so for the benefit of rulers. Yuri Knorozov and (*) Tatiana Proskouriakoff made important contributions to our understanding of the Mayan version of this activity, which combined logographic and phonetic elements. For 10 points, name this activity, most famously performed in the Americas by the Maya, in which language is represented with a system of abstract symbols.", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}